<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Astrologia reformata a reformation of the prognostical part of astronomy, vulgarly termed astrology : being an experimental detection and clear demonstration of the hitherto greatly mistaken, and dubiously by Robert Godson.</title>
            <author>Godson, Robert.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1696</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 67 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 27 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A42943</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing G965</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R21783</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12569226</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12569226</idno>
            <idno type="VID">63400</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A42943)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 63400)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 317:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Astrologia reformata a reformation of the prognostical part of astronomy, vulgarly termed astrology : being an experimental detection and clear demonstration of the hitherto greatly mistaken, and dubiously by Robert Godson.</title>
                  <author>Godson, Robert.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 51 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for George Sawbridge ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1696.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Astrology --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:63400:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:63400:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Aſtrologia Reformata:</hi> A Reformation of the Prognoſtical Part OF ASTRONOMY, Vulgarly Termed ASTROLOGY.</p>
            <p>BEING An Experimental Detection, and clear Demonſtration of the hitherto greatly miſtaken, and dubiouſly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverted Grounds and Principles of that unvaluable Science.</p>
            <p>And to this Firſt Eſſay is alſo annexed the (Never yet publickly given) true Poſitures at the Birth, and a Prediction of the Death, of the preſent <hi>French</hi> King.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> ROBERT GODSON.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>George Sawbridge,</hi> at the Three <hi>Flower-de-luces</hi> in <hi>Little-Britain,</hi> 1696.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:63400:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:63400:2"/>
            <head>To the Moſt Illuſtrious Brother<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood of Wiſdom, the Royal Philoſophical Society of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Gentlemen,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IT can neither with Truth nor Modesty be denied, but muſt (and will by all truly Aſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>philar Spirits) be freely and thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully Acknowledged, that thoſe many accurate Obſervations of the places and motions of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Bodies, which have been happily and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtriouſly made in the preſent and ſome late prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Ages (after Mankind was awak'd from that Monk-rock'd Security in which it had been lull'd for ſeveral generations, and Learning and Religion in ſome meaſure reſtor'd to their genuine uſe and deſign, of being means to attain to a due know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of God, and even ſenſible conviction of his Nature and Attributes, and to be profitable helps to direct us in our Affairs and Converſations,) have by the diligence and Induſtry of ſundry Learned Men of great skill and Dexterity in Coſmometrical Rations, Proportions, and Opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, been ſo well and ingeniouſly uſed and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:63400:3"/>to the end intended by the laborious Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vators, that they have greatly advanced that part of <hi>Sydereal</hi> Science, above what it had ever before attain'd to, if not almoſt to its utmoſt pitch of perfection.</p>
            <p>Yet is it alſo but too bewailably manifeſt that the Inſtitution of Coelestial Obſervations, and the thence detection and deduction of Planetary places and motions, and compoſure of Astronomick Tables, have of late been generally undertaken, by perſons little skilled, if not rather wholly Ignorant, of <hi>Sydereal</hi> ſignifications; and ſuch as knew little elſe concerning the Heavenly Bodies, beſide an uncertain and imperfect notion and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of their number, order, revolutional periods, the quality of their orbs, and frame of the Mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dane ſyſtem, and the craft of wielding a Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drant or Teleſcope, and of performing the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Trigonometrical operations; With which imperfect ſtock of Astral Skill, many have of late undertaken to frame Tables of the Heavenly motions, and do as confidently ſet up for <hi>Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomers,</hi> as if they had the knowledge of <hi>Daniel</hi> or <hi>Abraham.</hi> A pretence altogether as Abſurd and ridiculous, as if one ſhould take upon him to write a Medical Diſpenſatory, without any farther knowledge of Herbs and other Simples, than only a lame and defective notice of their number, colour, ſhape, places of growth, yearly ſeaſons, and other meer ſenſible accidents and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Circumſtances.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:63400:3"/>
            <p>And in regard of the great mysteriouſneſs of uranical portentations and the conſequent difficulty of truly understanding them; which requires not only common Reaſon and Diſcretion, and a fame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or-gain-ſpurr'd diligence and Industry, by which alone the Metrical or Mathematical part of this Science may be laudably practis'd and culti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vated, and accordingly now-a-days commonly is ſo; But alſo a particularly adapted Temper and Capacity (<hi>Aſtronomers</hi> as well as <hi>Poets,</hi> being rather the handy-work of Nature, than either of Art or Education:) A propenſion to it purely for its own ſake, and a ſpirit unbyaſſed by lucre and partiality, without which the greateſt endeavours will prove utterly vain and fruitleſs. And finding alſo that the unhappy thirſt of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular gain, and of the frothy reputation of va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious knowledge, is now ſo predominant in the minds of the far greater part of the pretended Votaries of Wiſdom, and (amongſt the reſt) of the Profeſſors and purſuers of this Science; Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gating (or rather ſeducing) them vain-gloriouſly to tamper with ſo many ſeveral Studies, and thoſe alſo utterly unneceſſary, and widely irrela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive to each other, any one of which (to be duly skillful therein) were alone enough to employ the whole time and faculties of any one Man, That they never become competent, and much leſs perfect in any; but are generally ſo weak, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect, and inſufficient, that their practice is commonly ſucceſsleſs or pernicious to their Clients,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:63400:4"/>and no leſs Ignominious and diſcrediting to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. It may ſtill be ſadly ſaid and lamented, that <hi>Aſtronomy</hi> is but (or hardly) half restor'd, being but (as <hi>Adam</hi> before his Inſpiration) a meer Body without a Soul.</p>
            <p>For we live in an Age wherein as well the matter as the methods of Study and Learning are choſen rather for their faſhionableneſs, and for their publick esteem among Gowned or Estated Men, eſpecially who have long practis'd and profeſs'd them (though a Divine Pen has long ago aſſur'd us, that great Men are not always Wiſe, nor the Aged univerſally Men of under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing) than for their own Intrinſick dignity or excellency; And rather for their promiſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to the ſecular Fame, Promotion, or advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of their Profeſſors, than their tendency or neceſſity to the Benefit or Utility of ſuch as conſult or employ them. And wherein Youth is by the modern unhappy methods of Education, kept ſo long in the Porch of Wiſdom's Temple, in Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning a parcel of ſilly miſ-called Arts and Old Foreign Tongues, little or nothing neceſſary for any but wrangling Clerkers (who are but a ſmall and the most needleſs part of the Profeſſors of Science) and in Conning and Contemplating thoſe Paganiſh Fictions, Dotages, and Macrologi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Impertinencies, contained in the Books com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly uſed for that purpoſe; That they never are permitted to enter her inner Courts, or have but a very ſmall time to abide there, and much too
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:63400:4"/>ſhort to gain a true knowledge of her ſolid my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steries. Beſide that their native faculties are ſo distorted and depraved by ſuch frivolous and Sophistical (pretended neceſſary) preparations, and their Heads and Fanſies ſo stuff'd and cloy'd with Idle and Abstracted (and mostly or gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally Erroneous) Notions, who leave no time nor room for ſound and practical knowledge: That if the Laws of the Land, or the weakneſs of their Patrons or Clients did not contribute to enſure them an ample or competent livelihood, the ſoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity of their knowledge, and ſucceſs of their practice, would never be able to procure it, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by <hi>Phyſick, Aſtronomy,</hi> or <hi>Divinity,</hi> the three great branches of Mystical Science: Each of which may abundantly be proved to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly corrupted and erroneous, even where they are vulgarly reputed and most confidently pretended to be most pure and Orthodox.</p>
            <p>Neither indeed can it poſſibly be otherwiſe, when ſuch an invincible variety not only of ſpeculative, but even of the profoundest and most difficult practical Arts and Studies, are undertaken by one individual Perſon, for whom any one of them alone were ſufficient, though as highly fitted and qualified for it, as God and Nature do enable any to be; nothing being now and for ſome Ages paſs'd more common, not only in Colleges and Univerſities, but in other places abroad in the World alſo, than for one and the ſelf ſame Perſon openly to Study, Profeſs,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:63400:5"/>and practice Arts and Sciences ſo vast in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and mostly or wholly ſo irrelative to one another, as are <hi>Medicine, Logick, Rhetorick,</hi> Natural <hi>Philoſophy, Aſtronomy,</hi> and all the ſeveral parts of <hi>Mathematicks</hi> and <hi>Geo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metry; Latin, Greek, Hebrew, Chaldee, Syriack,</hi> and ſundry other both Ancient and Modern Languages, ſometimes a dozen or fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen together; <hi>Muſick, Drawing, Painting, Phyſick, Aſtrology,</hi> and ſome others; or at least ſuch a conſiderable plurality of theſe, as that any modest and honeſt minded Man, who will not belye his Capacity to advance his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation (as it is too plain very many do) may eaſily perceive and will freely confeſs them not masterable to any competent perfection (ſave only to make an empty noiſe and ſhew before ſuch as little understand them) by any one Man whatſoever. And ſome of which are not only im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinent too, but even inconſistent with a due proſecution and intellection of the other; for what uſe of <hi>Logick, Rhetorick,</hi> or <hi>Geometry</hi> is there in the practice of <hi>Phyſick,</hi> which alſo is of it ſelf alone a Science large enough for any one Man to master, and the like might be ſaid of ſundry others. And albeit that Astrological Information may be of good uſe to a Phyſician, (as well as Medical Instructions to an Astro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomer, and to many other kinds of Perſons and Profeſſors beſide) yet does it not therefore follow that he must of neceſſity Study both Sciences
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:63400:5"/>himſelf, (for then every Man ſhould be master of all Arts and Trades, becauſe he has oftentimes uſe for them.) But he rather ſhould in his practice of the one, derive and receive all neceſſary helps by the other, from ſuch as make it their whole Study and Profeſſion; and the ſame may be ſaid of Tongues, and all other Arts and Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies: for while Men apply their Minds to ſo many ſeveral Sciences, each of which is ſo vast and profound, and ſo little pertinent or related to the rest, they only become meer pratling ſmat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terers in all, but are really Dexterous and ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent in none.</p>
            <p>Hence it comes that this tranſcendant Scien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, the most precious gem amongst the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of Wiſdom, the clearest Glaſs to behold Almighty Power, and the only Image of Divine Omniſciency; which the unbounded goodneſs of its ſupream Eternal Author, has ordained for the uſe and instruction of Man, to direct his ſteps in this vale of tryal and Tribulation, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he is wholly left to his own fate and diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and to his native will and diſpoſition in the choice of good or evil, to ſhift for himſelf the best he can, though not without gracious pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of providential reliefs and affistances upon his humble and earnest prayers to obtain them, in all ſuch times and caſes of extream affliction and adverſity, wherein his own Wit and indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stry fail him; and to enlighten his understan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding clearly to ſee into the dark corners of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:63400:6"/>and futurity; that he may not run blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold into places and enterpriſes, nor be taken unawares like a Bird in a ſnare, when an evil time comes ſuddenly upon him: Is become ſo utterly depraved and corrupted, that what now commonly paſſes by its name, is very little elſe but a heap of folly and falſehood; and ſo far from any appearance, and from ſhewing any effects of a divine and beneficial ordinance, that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny are Opinion'd there is no ſuch Science in nature; whatever others do affirm of its truth and excellency, is nothing but Fancy and Deluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; whereby this ſacred Lamp of Divine and infinite Wiſdom, which affords all ſatisfaction that the mind of Man can deſire, concerning any thing past, preſent, or future, is dwindl'd into ſmoke and ſnuff, and fallen to the lowest degrees of contempt with many even of good knowledge and capacity, the ſacred and venera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble name and Title of <hi>Aſtronomy,</hi> being now-a-days wholly attributed to and arrogantly aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med and uſurped by the bare Metrical or Mathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matical part of it, which is no more but its very husk or ſhell. It being ſadly and ſhamefully obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vable, that the Profeſſors of this as well as of other mysterious and profound Sciences, do, through a baſe thirſt after advantage and applauſe, and a ſordid itch to gain the repute and benefits of a great and faſhionable variety of skill and knowledge, not apply their Minds ſo wholly and ſolely to this ſublime and immenſe Science, (the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:63400:6"/>known fame and benefits of which alone if duly known and understood, were enough to ſatisfie any one modest Man) as is requiſite to a full or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent perfection therein. To which they afford but ſome ſmall part of only their ſpare hours, though vaſt and profound enough to employ their whole time and faculties, ſo that their skill and practice cannot but be as they are, and as I am even unwilling to think, and very much more to mention.—</p>
            <p>The diſpleaſing obſervation of thoſe diſ-inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious proceedings, and the ſway of a ſtrong in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination and affection (by many affirm'd to be the certain ſymptom of an equal Adaption) to this talleſt and beautifulleſt bravch of natural know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge; occaſion'd by the ſight of ſome rutilous ſpecks of Truth diſcovered and found to be yet unextinguiſhed, in ſtirring up the modern rubbiſh of its ruins, have prevaild with me to relinquiſh other employments more promiſing to my ſecular advantage, and for ſome conſiderable time to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quester my ſelf almost wholly from the World, ſo as to be but little publickly concern'd there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, that ſo I might gain the greater leiſures and opportunities to dive into the depths of this Science; for the certain diſcovery of whoſe ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lime and excellent mysteries, rejecting the ficti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Volumes and veluminous fictions of meer gueſſing pretenders, as well ancient as modern; and laying aſide all other practical Arts and Studies no way pertinent nor ſerviceable to this;
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:63400:7"/>I have cloſely applied my thoughts for ſeveral years together, to an experimentary examination of the Heavens immediately themſelves, by a careful and impartial collation and diſcuſſion of ſundry ſignificant coeleſtial faces and poſitures concerning one and the ſame particular, the only true method of making and gaining experience: And this not only for the ad-invention of the practical rules of this Science, but alſo for the tryal of its principles and rudiments, to find which of thoſe now variouſly delivered by ſundry Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors for ſuch, or whether none of thoſe, and what others beſide, are the only true and genuine. And herein as my ends have been honeſt, my affections impartial, my endeavours great, and my deſires vehement, ſo by the favour and aid of the ſovereign Author of Wiſdom, my Travels have been not unproportionably ſucceſsful, but ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectual to the diſcovery of many great Truths ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver hitherto known in the Chriſtian World; and to the perfection and clarification of many others, whereof though ſome in former days have had ſome fleeting glimpſes, yet was it with ſo much dimneſs and uncertainty, as render'd them wholly uſeleſs and unprofitable.</p>
            <p>And though I ſhall not yet lay claim to ſuch a degree of perfection therein, as to make all the predictions, and anſwer all the enquiries proper thereto and poſſible thereby (for what one Man can be ſufficient for theſe things, who found the Science ſo defective and corrupt as I did)
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:63400:7"/>yet I ſhall I undertake to diſcloſe and unfold ſo many great Truths and excellent Mysteries there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, hitherto utterly concealed and unknown, and many others heretofore but darkly and dubiouſly underſtood, as ſhall be abundantly pleaſing and acceptable to all who impartially examine and make uſe of them, and which ſhall be at leaſt as conducive to advance both the Truth and Credit of the prognoſtical part of <hi>Aſtronomy,</hi> as even the very beſt of the many late obſervers and diſcuſſers of coeleſtial motions have contributed to the preſent improvements of the Mathema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical; and ſhall abundantly prove to all who are endued with Reaſon, Judgment, and Modeſty, that the great pains and expences employ'd by many, in making ſuch obſervations, and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recting and perfecting the Doctrine of the ſaid motions, are uſeful and ſerviceable not only to the mean and ſhallow arts and purpoſes of <hi>Geography, Navigation,</hi> and the civil di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction of Years, Months, and Days, (all which low and inconſiderable ends, which wholly or moſtly tend rather to the gratification of Luxury and a needleſs-curioſity, than to promote any of the genuine ends of true knowledge, may be ſufficiently ſerv'd without any ſuch great ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actneſs;) but to other ends as great and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent as the Heavens are high, their face illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious, their greatneſs ſtupendious, their courſes and motions conſtant and harmonious, and Mens endeavours to diſcover them expenſive and labo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious;
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:63400:8"/>and that the excellent Myſteries contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in and diſcoverable by this unparallell'd Science, even though we ſhould wholly lay aſide all prognoſtical uſe thereof (which yet may be very great and beneficial) but uſing it only as an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genious ſpeculation (as is all or moſt of that kind of <hi>Philoſophy</hi> now in chief repute,) diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>playing that exact and wonderful harmony which Almighty God has ordained between the motions and poſitions of the Heavenly Bodies, and the actions and events of all ſublunary creatures, is a thouſand times more valuable and worthy to be prized and affected by all who delight to conſider the handy works of God, than that fanciful Fooloſophy now ſo much in vogue, of making blind gueſſes at the ſecret undiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verable reaſons and cauſes of both the ordinary and extraordinary effects and appearances in na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture (ſuch as Comets, Magnetiſm, Winds, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) and at the meaning and deſign of old defaced In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriptions, and new found Relicks of Antiquity, and many other ſuch trivial and uſeleſs matters, which many now-a-days make a great noiſe and ſtir with; or I may rather ſay it doth as much exceed them, as the Heavens ſurmount the Earth, and the Wiſdom of God tranſcendeth that of Men.</p>
            <p>Neither do I doubt but ſtrongly and reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly hope, and with God's Aſſiſtance fully pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, by the uſe and help of due means and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours, to raiſe it to that degree of claritude
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:63400:8"/>and perfection, that all who apply themſelves hereafter thereunto, with honeſt and ſincere af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections and intentions, and a deſire to be thereby ſerviceable to their generation; and who by cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain and never failing rules which ſhall fully and faithfully be given for that purpoſe, do find themſelves duly qualified and capacitated for this Study, ſhall by their own experience and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours be ſpeedily able to ſupply what is wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting from mine; and by their honeſt and inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious practice and exerciſe thereof, and daily demonſtration of its excellent uſe, and of the great good that may be done thereby, declare it as fit and neceſſary for the Courts and Dominions of Chriſtian Prinoes, as it was and ſtill is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted to be (though but very dimly and imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly understood) in theſe of <hi>Heathens</hi> and <hi>Mahometans.</hi> This ſaid Mantical or Progno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stical part of <hi>Aſtronomy</hi> (commonly though leſs properly termed by another name,) being a Science wholly conſisting of real wonders, as great as ever the power of God did expoſe to the ſight of Mankind; who may thereby daily behold the Tragedies and Comedies of ſecular affairs pre-act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Planets on the Stage of Heaven, in a far more exact and elegant manner than they are uſually re-acted in Earthly Theatres; and thence may attain to a competent Aſſimilation of his Maker's Omniſcience, in the Knowledge of what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever his Mind or Spirit can deſire concerning any thing paſt, preſent, or to come: And this
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:63400:9"/>by Means far more ſure and infallible, than the ordinary ones of Hiſtory, Report and Conjecture.</p>
            <p>As a Teſtimony of my Succeſſes and Improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in this Science, and an Earneſt of what I promiſe and purpoſe further to perform therein, I here offer to Your Sagacious Worthineſſes (whoſe ſeveral diſtinguiſhing Titles and Dignities I ſhall not now inſiſt on) the following Obſervations and Experiments; not by craving Your Patronage, and by the Prefixure of Your Name, to concile unto them any greater Favour or Eſteem abroad in the World, than what their proper Merit ſhall be able ſelfly to procure them; a Shift, which, though now very uſual with many others, yet am I as far from deſiring as I hope theſe are from needing it: But rather to recommend to your Favour and Eſteem this ancient and venerable Science, which as I am ſorry to have been hitherto neglected by You, ſo I am in hope, that by means of the enſuing Illuſtrations, it will henceforth appear at least as worthy as any thing elſe whatſoever, to be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rolled amongst the Subjects of Your generous Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſitions. And therefore, hoping and deſiring Your zealous Co-operation herein, ſo far as the Mattter ſhall be found meritorions thereof, (which for the future I do not doubt but it will,) I ſhall here with all due Reſpectfulneſs conclude, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways humbly remain an unfeigned Well-wiſher to the proſperous Succeſs of all Your ingenious Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vails and Endeavours.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>R. G.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:63400:9"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ranomantia Reformata.</head>
            <div n="1" type="essay">
               <head>
                  <hi>The Firſt ESSAY.</hi> Shewing how to rectifie the Genitures of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed Perſons, by the two principal and moſt common Accidents of Humane Life, namely, Marriage, and Natural Death. And thereby preparing a plain and eaſie Way to diſcover the true Method of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming the ſame by all others. And con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently, affording a never failing Key to unlock the whole Treaſury of Genethlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Myſteries: Which has hitherto lain hid from Ages and Generations; but is now here partly, and ſhall ſhortly be more fully laid open to the Sight of all Men.</head>
               <p>FOraſmuch as that I now undertake and intend to unfold the ſublime and ſacred Myſteries of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Science, and to declare how and in what manner are repreſented and portended thereby, the Actions and Events of all Earthly Creatures; whether whole
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:63400:10"/>Nations in general, or ſingle Perſons in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular. It ſeems moſt convenient to begin with that part of the ſaid Science, which concerns the Genitures of Mankind, and ſhews how by the Poſitures of Heaven at the Moment of a Perſon's Birth, or firſt En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance into the World, to fore-ſee the ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry Actions, Undertakings, Changes, Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions, and all other Circumſtances and Occurrences of his Life, and the Time and Manner of his final End, or Death: As be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Branch of this Divine Skill, which many account, of all others, the moſt uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful; and therefore is by moſt Modern Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors chiefly purſu'd and cultivated. And in the performance hereof, it will be ſafeſt and ſureſt, and conſequently fitteſt, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin with thoſe Actions and Events which are common to all, or the greater part of Mankind; and are alſo the Extremities of their ſeveral Kinds, and therefore moſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious to Experimentation, and their ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying Particulars moſt remarkable and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernable. Which ſaid moſt common Actions and Events I affirm to be, Marriage, and Natural Death: Of which, the former is the Extremity of Love and Courtſhip; and the latter, of Diſeaſe and Sickneſs; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing both of them incident to very many, their true Signs in the Heavens are much more ſpeedily and eaſily diſcoverable, than
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:63400:10"/>are the Signs of Chances that happen only to ſome few; and are therefore the ſureſt means of Genethliacal Rectification.</p>
               <p>Moreover, the better to prepare the Way to go through with this weighty Task, I muſt in the firſt place require my Reader to be moderately (if not perfectly) verſed in, and acquainted with, at leaſt ſome one Treatiſe introductive to this Science; of which there are already ſo many publiſhed, even in the Vulgar Tongue of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, by Mr. <hi>Lilly,</hi> Mr. <hi>Gadbury,</hi> Mr. <hi>Coley,</hi> and many others, that all who have them not already, may very ſpeedily provide themſelves. And nextly, I ſhall lay down ſome fundamental Maxims, or Propoſitions, whereon to raiſe, and firmly ſuperſtruct my intended Genethliacal Edifice; ſome of which are wholly novel to the World; and though others of them have languidly glimpſed to the Apprehenſions of ſome few Authors, yet ſo very dimly, ſeldomly, and uncertainly, that they plainly appear to be doubtful and unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved whether they were true or no, or any whit more true than ſome which by others are oppoſed unto them: Whereas I certainly know, and ſhall in due time abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly prove them to be beyond all Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That the only true, effectual, ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant, and Divinely ordained, as well as
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:63400:11"/>moſt rational Diviſion of the Heavens into thoſe Prognoſticative Partitions which <hi>Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomers</hi> term Houſes, is that which divides the viſible or apparent Sphere of each parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular place or point of the Earth, whether City, Town, Houſe, or other place of Birth or Reſidence, into twelve equal Shares or Portions, by Lines meeting at the North and South Points of the <hi>Horizon,</hi> and equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſtant in the ſaid apparent Sphere's own Vertical Aequator, or Circle paſſing from Eaſt to Weſt.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That thoſe Eſſential Dignities and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilities, and Geocentrical Configurations of the Planets, handed down to us in theſe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Ages, by <hi>Ptolomy,</hi> from the ancient <hi>Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dean</hi> and <hi>Aegyptian Astronomers,</hi> are ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient, of themſelves alone, to ſignifie all things properly ſignificable by ſuch Matters, either in a Nativity, or any other Face of Heaven; and are alſo the only true and ſignificant Dignities, Debilities and Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gurations, by Almighty God ordained ſo to do: The <hi>Keplerian</hi> Aſpects, <hi>Placidian</hi> Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliarities, and pretended Planitary Digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Debilities vended to the World by ſome late and modern Authors, being only the haſty, groundleſs, ill digeſted Fancies of raſh and idle Brains, and ſingle vain-glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious perſons; who, though but little read or skilled in this Science, and as little ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:63400:11"/>with the true Methods of making Experience therein, to which, by reaſon of their many other Studies, they afford but the very leaſt part of their Time and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours, would nevertheleſs pretend them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and fain be thought able, by their very few and ſeldom Searches and Trials, to diſcover the true Grounds and Principles of this Science, better than the whole many<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aged Succeſſion of the zealous and indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious Ancients, who wholly devoted their Time and Endeavours thereunto.</p>
               <p n="3">3. That in all Humane Genitures, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Males, or Females, the firſt Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage is always ſignified by ſome Direction of the Mid-Heaven to the Body, or ſome Ray of the Lord of the Seventh Houſe, agreeable to the Quality and Succeſs of the Marriage, who or whatſoever Planet the ſaid Lord of the Seventh be: For <hi>Saturn</hi> and <hi>Mercury</hi> are in this caſe as effectual and ſignificant as the <hi>Moon</hi> or <hi>Venus;</hi> and theſe latter no more ſo than the former, but only by their being Lords of the Seventh; and never but when they are ſo; neither do the Directions of the Aſcendent, <hi>Sun,</hi> or <hi>Moon,</hi> to any Planet or Aſpect whatſoever, ever produce or ſignifie Wedlock; as ſhall in due time and place be plainly proved.</p>
               <p n="4">4. That Natural Death, by Sickneſs or Diſtemper of Body, is in all Nativities, of
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:63400:12"/>whatſoever Kind or Sex, denoted and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhed by ſome Direction of the Cuſp of the Aſcendent, or Firſt Houſe to the Malefical Body or Beam of ſome Lord of the Sixth Houſe, or elſe to the <hi>Moon's</hi> Sou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thern Node, commonly called the <hi>Dragon's-Tale.</hi> And in this caſe, the evil Aſpects, even of <hi>Jupiter</hi> and <hi>Venus;</hi> are full as effica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious as thoſe of <hi>Saturn</hi> or <hi>Mars;</hi> neither of whom have any Power or Significancy of Natural Death, but when they are Lords of the ſaid Sixth Houſe; and then ſo have the other five Planets alſo; that is to ſay, when any of them is Lord of the Sixth. The Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections of the <hi>Sun</hi> or <hi>Moon,</hi> and much leſs of the pretended parts of Life or Fortune, being never effectual or ſignificant of Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Death; and the ordinary vulgar Rules of chuſing Givers of Life and Death, being utterly fabulous, and extreamly erroneous.</p>
               <p n="5">5. That not all ſuch Directions as thoſe mentioned in the two laſt preceding Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions, are always effective of Marriage, or Natural Death; but only when the promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing or Menacing Planet is qualified with ſome certain Poſitions, and other Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, which are requiſite to render the ſaid Direction effectually Mortal or Conjugal, and free from certain others that may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct or impede its being ſo; without which aid requiſite Qualification and Vacancy, (of
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:63400:12"/>which there are ſeveral Kinds, that ſhall in due time and place be declared,) the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive may perſiſt in Life and Singlehood, notwithſtanding any ſuch Direction. The Ignorance or Inconſideration of which Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertion hath cauſed ſome late and modern Profeſſors to run headlong into the greateſt Abſurdities; vainly, weakly and raſhly concluding, that becauſe (in their Eſtimate, or Corrected Figures) the Aſcendent over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs'd the Body or ill Aſpect of ♄ or ♂, in ſome Nativities, eſpecially wherein, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their rules, it was not Giver of Life, therefore ſuch a Direction could never kill in any.</p>
               <p n="6">6. That though Rectification by either of theſe ſaid Accidents, if duly and diſcreetly performed, will yield and produce the true Figure of Birth ſo ſufficiently near as that Judgment may by a skillful Artiſt be ſafely given thereof, both as to the Native's gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Fate, and Time of his particular Actions and Occurrences, without any conſiderable Errour in point of Time, but what may be redreſſed by other Means; yet is it not to be expected, that from any Figure ſo recti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, the very Year or Month, and much leſs the Day of any other fore-going or following Accident, will be exactly pointed out by Directions only, ſo as that the Directional Diſtance between any two
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:63400:13"/>promiſing or threatning Bodies or Aſpects directed to, and the Temporal Diſtance be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the two Accidents ſignified by them, ſhould (eſpecially in Accidents which hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen many Years aſunder) be always pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually and preciſely equal; which I clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly find they never are, though never con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderably differing; but near enough for any neceſſary Occaſion of the Fore-know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of ſuch Matters: For albeit that the preciſe Year and Month, and poſſibly alſo the Day of an Action or Event may be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced and diſcovered from a Geniture ſo rectified, yet not by the alone Directions of the Nativity, as ſome have fanſied and ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſted, who, had their Meaſure of Time, and Method of Directing been never ſo true and genuine, (as it is evident they were not) yet the Errour in their Planets places would have thwarted ſuch a Co-incidence, and was manifeſtly the Cauſe of that punctual Agreement in ſome few Directions and Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidents; which they therefore fondly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded to be univerſal to all, and for which the beſt Tables yet extant are inſufficient.</p>
               <p>Theſe are all the fundamental Maxims (beſides what are common to the whole Science, and already publick from other Hands) which I think needful whereon to raiſe my intended Edifice; and which, as I have found them moſt indubitably true, by
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:63400:13"/>a clear and manifold Experience, ſo ſhall I by the ſame declare and evince them to be ſo to others alſo, even when and where it may to many ſeem altogether impoſſible: And though I could diſcharge my fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>promiſed Explication by many experienced Nativities, not only of my own private En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry, which by many Circumſtances I find, and am aſſured to have been nearly eſtima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and by which I have diſcovered the fore-given Propoſitions to be moſt true and certain; but alſo by many others already publiſhed by ſeveral, and in which I find the ſaid propoſitions to hold true alſo; am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply diſcuſſing and illuſtrating each indivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dual Geniture, by inſtancing all its known and conſiderable Accidents, and aſſigning them to their proper Directions, and ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſtrange Agreement that is between them, both as to Quality, Time, and all other Circumſtances, (ſave only the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned immaterial temporal Diſcrepan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, otherwiſe eaſily redreſſable,) yet ſhall I confine my ſelf to the number of only three, and thoſe alſo already publiſhed by others, and ſuch as are credibly ſaid and granted to have been obſerved with great or moderate Care, and ſhall by me be Aſtronomically proved to have been ſo accordingly, at leaſt near enough for an intelligent Practitioner truly to correct and reduce them.</p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:63400:14"/>
               <p>With this ſaid Number and Quality of Nativities I do the rather chuſe to begin my Explications; partly that none may ſuſpect or object them to be of my own Timing, or Eſtimation, a Crime wherewith ſome (how truly I know not) are now-a-days by others largely and loudly taxed; and partly becauſe that as a Threefold Cord is not eaſily broken ſo a Threefold Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny is not eaſily diſproved, nor reaſonably diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſted, being held ſufficient to ratifie the Matter debated, in all, as well Legal as Scientifical Deciſions. Neither ſhall I inſiſt on the Inſtance or Aſſignation of any other Accidents in theſe firſt illuſtrated Genitures, but of Marriage and Natural Death alone, unleſs they all three, and not only one or two of them, were concern'd therein; becauſe I intend to inſiſt upon nothing but what I give a threefold Proof of; as not at all ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proving of that unſatisfactory Method now followed and practiſed by the generality of our Profeſſors, who not only do confident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly offer to the World for true and exact, when rectified only by one ſingle Accident; and that alſo aſſigned to a Direction which has manifeſtly fai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>'d of effecting the ſame in many others, without giving or know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Reaſon why it ſhould do ſo: But do alſo give us practical Rules and Aphoriſms for the Judgment of a Nativity, deduced
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:63400:14"/>from only one ſingle Geniture, and which therefore ſeldom or never holds true in any other, to the great Diſcredit of themſelves, and of thoſe who credulouſly practiſe or judge by their Doctrines.</p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" rend="hr"/>
               <p>THE firſt Nativity which I ſhall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce, for the Eviction and Confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of my ſaid Propoſitions concerning Marriage and Natural Death, (intending to do the like for all other Principles and practical Rules of this Science, by degrees, and in due Seaſon,) is, that of the late King <hi>Charles</hi> II. In the Rectification where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, to reduce it from the eſtimate Time, to the true, as nearly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> can be done by acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dental Correction, I ſhall make uſe of the <hi>Sun</hi>'s mean daily Motion, as the Meaſure of Time for a Year: Not that I think this too fully, either natural or rational; or that it will yield an exact Equality between the Diſtance of Directions, and their ſignified Events; which I have already propoſed, as a thing not to be expected; but becauſe that, one time with another, it affords as great an Agreement both in all Nativities, and alſo in the various Accidents of one of the ſame Nativity, as any other Meaſure of Time that ever I ſaw propos'd, or could
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:63400:15"/>any way conceive or ſuſpect to be true and rational, or which had any the leaſt likeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood or appearance of being ſo. All and every of which ſaid ſeemingly rational Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures (ſave one or two which I have lately thought on, and ſhall very ſhortly bring to the Touch-ſtone) I have throughly tried by ſeveral experimented Genitures, but ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver found them to anſwer Expectation any more or nearer than this of mean Motion.</p>
               <p>And whereas ſome may captiouſly object, that this confeſſed Unexactneſs may be oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion'd by a miſtakeful Aſſignation of Acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents to improper Directions; To this I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, That I can give a poſitive General Rule, not only for the two grand Accidents aforeſaid, but alſo for ſeveral others; and expreſly nominate all thoſe Circumſtances and Qualifications requiſite to render the Promiſſor effective or ineffective of them; and prove by many indubitable Nativities, that the ſaid Directions fulfill'd or fail'd ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly: Which is more than ever was yet done by any Author, and than can poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly be done by the Rules and Methods they follow, who make or take ſo many both Significators and Promiſſors, for one and the ſame Accident, (as the <hi>Aſcendant, Mid-Heaven, Sun, Moon,</hi> and ſometimes <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune</hi> alſo, for Significators of Marriage; and <hi>Jupiter, Venus, Sol, Luna,</hi> and the <hi>Lord of the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:63400:15"/>Seventh,</hi> for Promiſſors; and the like for all other Accidents;) and ſo many ſorts of Aſpects, old and new, Mundane and Zo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diacal, that they can never miſs of a Dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction fit enough by their Method, to which to aſſign any Accident, and by which to rectifie any Nativity, without any great Change from the given Time, how much amiſs or miſtaken ſoever; nay, even though both the Birth, and the Time and Quality of the Accidents be merely and utterly feigned, and that no ſuch things really ever were; for having ſo many ſeveral Significa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors and Promiſſors as aforeſaid, they take that ſeemingly reſemblant Direction to ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie the Accident, which in their Eſtimate Figure happens pretty near the time of it, as in ſuch a Variety ſome or other of them cannot fail to do; and do frequently aſſign Accidents to Directions which they grant paſſed over without any ſuch Effects in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other Nativities, even when the Promiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor had the ſame or other equivalent Quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fications in both: And in each Nativity in which they aſſign any Accident to a Dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, they allow many other Directions to paſs over without the like Effects though they aſſign the fame unto them in ſeveral other Nativities. By all which Means, it is very common and eaſie to find a near Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Directions with Accidents, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:63400:16"/>impoſſible to miſs of it, at any Hour of the Day, how far ſoever from the true Time of Birth; and oftentimes much bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter at a wrong Time, than the right one; ſo that a certain Rectification is by theſe Methods impoſſible. Whereas, according to the Method by which I practiſe, (the Grounds whereof I have diſcover'd from ſundry Genitures of both my own and others Obſervation and Enquiry; and whoſe both given Year, Day and Hour, appear, and are proved by ſeveral obſerved and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated Circumſtances to have been very true, and the Moment nearly alſo,) it is ſcarce ever poſſible to find an Agreement of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections with Accidents, to any reaſonable or tolerable nearneſs, but at the true Time of Birth only; at which time they never fail to agree, and that alſo with as great an Exactneſs in Time, as can be ſhew<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d by any other Method whatſoever. All which is abundantly ſufficient to evince the Truth and Excellency of this.</p>
               <p>Theſe things being premiſed, and the aforeſaid Objection clear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d, I ſhall now pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to a Diſcuſſion of the Geniture of the Prince above-named; who is certainly known, and generally granted to have been born on <hi>Saturday, May</hi> the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>th, in the Year of Chriſt (according to Vulgar Account) 1630<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> near about Noon; ſome ſaying a
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:63400:16"/>little before, and others a little after: But Noon we may take for an Eſtimate ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently exact, in regard my Rule of Recti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication is ſufficient to lead me to the true Time of Birth, were it a whole Hour or two ſooner or later; for that about that time of the Day it yields no Agreement of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections with Accidents, but at one certain Point of Time only. Wherefore finding that at the ſaid Eſtimate Time the Mid-Heaven is poſſeſs'd by 17 Degrees and an half of the Sign <hi>Gemini,</hi> and that this Native was Royally married at almoſt 32 Years old, and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued till Death a Husband to the ſame Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, without either Divorce, or open Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like or Repentance, I conſider whether about that time of Day, and by the aforeſaid Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of Time, the Mid-Heaven do meet with any good Direction to the Body or Beam of the Lord of the Seventh, or of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Planet, who upon Rectification by ſuch a Direction, will be found to be Lord of the Seventh, at a diſtance agreeable to ſuch an Age: And accordingly, I find a Trine of <hi>Jupiter,</hi> who is not only Lord of the Seventh in the Eſtimate Figure, but alſo upon Recti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication by the ſaid Meaſure of Time, and Age of Marriage, is found to be ſo too; and gives the annexed Face of Heaven for the true Poſiture at Birth, with ſo ſmall a Diſtance from the given or eſtimate Time,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:63400:17"/>as is very conſiſtent and reconcilable with the common and daily diſcernible un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>exactneſs of Clocks, Watches, and Ocular Obſervations.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>astrological figure</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p>Thus have I rectified this Royal Geniture by one of the ſaid grand Accidents: And though many others do give us many Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vities for true and certain, upon only one ſingle Correction, yet I hold it not ſufficient nor ſatisfactory to do ſo. And therefore let us examine whether, according to the fore-given Rule, there happen in this Figure, corrected as before, any dangerous Direction of the Aſcendent to the Lord of the Sixth, at or near about the time of this Prince's Death: Upon which Examination I find,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:63400:17"/>that the Aſcendant comes to the Body of <hi>Saturn,</hi> Lord of the Sixth, nearly about that time, without any Diſcrepancy between the Diſtances of the Directions, and of the Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidents, but what is, and has always been allowed of, as uſual, by all the moſt skilful and experienc'd Artiſts in all Ages. And theſe two Directions do mutually confirm each other, not only by agreeing ſo nearly in Time, with their aſcribed Effects; but alſo by their being Lords of thoſe Houſes, which, according to the traditionally deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, frequently experienced, and general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly received Doctrines of this Science, do ſignifie the Means of the ſaid Accidents: And having alſo ſuch Qualifications and Poſitions in this preſent Geniture, as are ſufficient to render them effectual to thoſe Purpoſes.</p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" rend="hr"/>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>astrological figure</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p>But whereas ſome Curriſh-minded Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenders, whoſe Annual immodeſt Railleries ſeem to inſinuate, that they uſe this Science only as a Tool of Obloquy and Conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:63400:18"/>may captiouſly object, That I aſſign this Prince's Betrothal, rather than his Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, to the proper Direction, only for a Shift, becauſe it better agrees with that for his Death. I anſwer, That inſtead of jar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring at my ſo doing, they rather ought, as undoubtly every true Lover of Heavenly Knowledge will, be thankful for giving ſo fair an Occaſion of making ſo uſeful an En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry, whether Sponſation, or Conſumma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; eſpecially when conſiderably diſtant, or that the former happens, and never the latter, be the Time of the Direction's Inci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence: To the Deciſion of which Matter, though I could give ſome further Light, yet this here offer'd ſhall ſuffice for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent.</p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" rend="hr"/>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>astrological figure</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:63400:19"/>
               <p>I Might here proceed to a further Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of the Genuine Truth and Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty of theſe Rectifications, by particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhewing the wonderfully exact Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which, according to ſound and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver-failing Rules, which generally hold true in all Nativities, appears, and is to be found between the Poſitions, Configurations, and the other unmentioned Directions of each of the ſaid three Genitures, and the known Fates, Diſpoſitions, Events and Circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the reſpective Natives. And the like I could alſo do by the Figures of their ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Revolutions, for the Affairs and Occur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences of each particular Year, wherein any thing remarkable happen'd, or was done: As alſo by producing and diſcuſſing the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitures of many other deceaſed Perſons, and ſhewing the great and near Agreement of their Death and other Occurrences, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to a ſingle and determinate Rule for each, with the Quality and Time of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections which by the ſaid Rule do ſignifie them. But partly to omit a Superfluity of Teſtimonies, as unneceſſary; and partly becauſe the Time or Manner of Death of ſome of them is controverted, or void of Authentick Teſtimony; and partly becauſe divers of them never married, or that I have received no Account of the Time when;
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:63400:20"/>and chiefly for that I intend not to inſtance any Particulars, but what I give a threefold Proof of; which the fore-going three Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitures will not afford for any other Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters; I ſhall leave them to be the Subject of ſucceeding intended Eſſays.</p>
               <p>I could likewiſe give a further Confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the ſaid Truths, by examining the Genitures of ſundry Perſons who have mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed, and have had a Direction for their ſo doing, according to the fore-going Rule: But as they are ſtill living, or died ſome way un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturally, (the radical and directional Signs whereof do greatly differ from thoſe of the other, as well as from thoſe many blind Rules already given by many for judging it,) ſo has there happen'd no Direction yet, or not before their ſaid violent Deaths; which, according to my Rule, could denote a natural Expiration. But to avoid Prolixi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Superfluity, I ſhall do this only by the Nativity of the preſent <hi>French</hi> King; and that not ſo much in order to the ſaid Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation, as to clear a great Miſtake, or Uncertainty, which the Generality of the Profeſſors and Students of theſe three King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms are under, concerning the true <hi>Geneſis</hi> of this crafty Monarch.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>astrological figure</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p>This raking and deſigning Prince was Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally Wedded when aged about 20 Years and 6 Months, at the Acceſs of his Vertical Cuſp to the Trine of <hi>Jupiter,</hi> Lord of his Seventh Houſe; whoſe Qualifications here are ſuch as may render him fully effective of that Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident. And as this great Native is yet alive, ſo has there yet happen'd no Dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in this Celeſtial Tranſcript, which, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to my Rules for Death of all ſorts, could be in any manner mortal; neither is there any ſuch likely to happen, till the Aſcendant comes to the Quartile of <hi>Saturn,</hi> who is not only Lord of the Sixth, but other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe killingly qualified alſo. And this ſaid dangerous Direction takes place about the Sixty ſecond Year of his Age; about which time (the preciſe Year whereof may be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover'd by other Means, but not by Dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction alone) he will certainly and natural<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly expire, in ſpight of all the Means that can poſſibly be us'd to ſave him. Whoſe Death, though eagerly thirſted by many who pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly profeſs this Science; and who, by what they have already done concerning it, do declare they would readily and publick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:63400:21"/>predict it if they could, yet do plainly appear unable (and therefore afraid) to do it; thereby viſibly bewraying their own Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance and Inſufficiency for all ſuch Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertakings, and Performances.</p>
               <p>Thus have I compleated all that for the preſent I intended, concerning the two Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectional Propoſitions aforeſaid; fully pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing, by God's Permiſſion and Aſſiſtance, to do as much for the Confirmation of the other Propoſitions alſo, and for the Detection and Illuſtration of all other Principles and Practical Rules of this Science. And though, in handling the fore-going Genitures, I have neither conſider'd ſome Circumſtances of ſome of the given Accidents, nor uſed ſome other and further Means of Correction; which would yield a ſomewhat nearer A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement than will reſult from what is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready done; yet theſe ſingle (and only pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parative) Rectifications, and the manifeſted near and regular Agreement of Directions with Accidents, are enough to render the Propoſitions ſtrongly probable: Which is all that I either deſigned, or deſired.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:63400:22"/>
               <head>A Particular Account and Enumeration of the ſeveral Sources, Cauſes and Occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of the many erroneous Principles, Doctrines and Aphoriſms, now in, or falſly father'd upon the Heavenly Science of <hi>Prognoſtical Aſtronomy.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">1. MAny are ſo fooliſhly and careleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly credulous, as to receive for abſolutely true and certain, whatſoever has been deliver'd as ſuch by the more ancient and more famous Authors in this Science, without either receiving from the ſaid Authors, or making for themſelves, any Experimentary Proof or Demonſtration of its Verity; and this even in the Grounds and firſt Rudiments hereof: Which alſo are in ſome Particulars variouſly deliver'd, ſome ſaying one thing, and ſome another; as guided by their own bare Fancies, (by them miſ-called Reaſon,) without the leaſt Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony from any certain or rational Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Having eſpouſed ſuch affirmed Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples as they fancifully conceit (rather than ſolidly find and know) to be genuine, they then, upon Suppoſition (or rather ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſly
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:63400:22"/>confident Concluſion) of their being ſo, do by the bare Light of their own weak Reaſon, without taking or ſeeking any Help from Experience, (were they able to make a right Uſe of it,) forge ſuch Rules as to them ſeem ſuitable to thoſe Principles; and accordingly, becauſe the Ninth Houſe is ſaid to ſignifie Religion, (which they on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly know by Reading or Hear-ſay,) there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord of the Firſt in the Ninth, or the Lord of the Ninth in the Firſt, muſt needs denote a holy, gracious Native. And a Thouſand more ſuch ſhallow, and daily thwarted Whimſeys.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The very Proper Names of the Signs, given them only for Diſtinction, by ſuch as little underſtood their Qualities; and mere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly becauſe at that time poſſeſſed by ſome Conſtellations very imperfectly reſembling the Things by whoſe Names they were cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, are by many very ridiculouſly made a Rule whereby to judge of their ſignified Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures and Diſpoſitions, and of the Inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and Propenſions of thoſe Natives, whoſe perſonal Significations are placed in them. And therefore, if in <hi>Taurus,</hi> the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty muſt be laborious; if in <hi>Leo,</hi> fierce and cruel; if in <hi>Scorpio,</hi> falſe and treacherous; if in <hi>Aquarius,</hi> gentle and courteous; and the like of all other Signs, and for the moſt part quite contrary to what they really are,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:63400:23"/>as are theſe Whimſeys concerning the Four here mentioned. And the ſame is done concerning the Planets alſo, as confidently, as if <hi>Adam</hi> had been their God-father.</p>
               <p n="4">4. This Science is inſpected and ſtudied by many; not in any vertuous Inclination to conſider the Works of God, and contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plate the wonderful Harmony hereby diſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nible between Fate and Nature, and to be thereby ſerviceable to their Generation; but merely in hope of reaping Profit to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves by the Practice of it, if they ſee any likelihood or poſſibility of ſo doing: Or through a ſneaking Itch of Praiſe and Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauſe; as thinking that if they can but tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly predict Things to come, it will be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted a glorious Buſineſs, and make them be every where gazed at with Admiration. And all whoſe Studies are influenc'd by ſuch Ends, do generally prove but ignorant Botchers in any Myſtical Science whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever.</p>
               <p n="5">5. The moſt of thoſe who profeſs this Science, or pretend an Affection thereunto, do buſie themſelves in ſo many other Arts and Studies beſide, no way pertinent or ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary hereunto, and only becauſe they are gainful, creditable, or faſhionable, that it is not poſſible for them to be compleat or competent in any, but eſpecially in this, which is, of all others, the moſt myſterious
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:63400:23"/>and ſublime, yet is commonly afforded but the very-leaſt part of their Time and Endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours, though vaſt and profound enough to employ the whole of both: Concerning which; ſo much has been already delivered elſewhere, that I need not ſay much here.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Many who make a deeper Search here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>into, than by bare Speculation, and (con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitedly) rational Deduction and Inference; and who ſpend ſome Time and Pains in grounding their Knowledge upon their own Experience, by comparing Fates and Acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents with Radical Poſitions and Directions, do yet too haſtily receive, and too credu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly ſtick to eſtimate Times of Birth, and the given or computed Times of other ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificant Faces of Heaven, received from the Mouths or Hands of others; and ſuch Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions, and other Sydereal Particulars as they find in theſe erroneous Copies of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, they take, without further Scruple, or Examination, to be the true Signs of the ſubſequent Events and Occurrences: Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as, did they but privately obſerve, and care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully compute ſome few Times of that kind themſelves, and compare them with the Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts taken by, or received from others, they would very frequently find a wide Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agreement. And therefore, ſuch as deſire to be perfect and exact, ought, from Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervations and Computations of their own,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:63400:24"/>or other curious Artiſts, truly and carefully made, by proper and ſufficient Means, to frame and diſcover Rules concerning, at leaſt, ſome ſmall Plurality of notable Acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents, eſpecially Death and Marriage; and theſe will greatly help to diſcover the true Signs of other Events, and the true Times of other leſs accurate Obſervations.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Another very miſ-guiding Courſe, fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low'd by many Experimentators, and a great Overſight committed by them, is, That they reſt ſatisfied with ſome very few (and oftentimes one alone) of a Native's Accidents; and this they uſually aſſign to the next agreeably good or bad Direction, which, in their Eſtimate Figure, happens about that time; requiring no more, but that, in a general manner, it reſemble (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to received Rudiments) the Quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Event, as to Goodneſs or Badneſs, without heeding or conſidering whether, in all other Nativities, it effect that ſame kind of Accident in particular: Whereby it comes to paſs, that we frequently find the ſame kind of Direction given for Marriage in one Nativity, for Preferment in another, for Legacy in another, for the Birth of a Child in another, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> never heeding any more, but that the Direction happen (in their gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven Figure) about the ſame time with the Accident, and be, in general, good or bad,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:63400:24"/>as that is: Whereas, did they diligently en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire and know the whole Series of a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive's regardable Accidents, and turn their Eſtimate (if it needed a Change) to ſuch a corrected Face of Heaven, as afforded an Agreement, both in Time and Quality, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween all the ſeveral Accidents and Dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, it would much more rightly guide them to make a right Aſſignation, and thence to diſcover the proper Effects of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Directions more truly; the Omiſſion of which Enquiry, and Lack of which Knowledge, is the Cauſe that many good and bad Accidents are attributed to (accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly good or bad) Directions, which do not at all ſignifie them.</p>
               <p n="8">8. The Reports and Accounts of the Time and Quality of Actions and Acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents, both publick and private, are ſome or oftentimes amiſs, and may thereby cauſe an erroneous Notion of the Significations and Effects of a Planetary Direction and Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guration. Wherefore an honeſt Student ought to be very careful not to be over-haſty in believing Relations or Hiſtories, without ſome Plurality of Teſtimonies, or other very aſſuring Circumſtances; nor to make his Experience by any but ſuch as he is, by thoſe Means, very ſure of, and beyond the Danger and Poſſibility of Deception.</p>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:63400:25"/>
               <p n="9">9. It muſt be confeſſed, that the long Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance of the true Syſtem of the Heavens, and of the Frame and Order of the Plane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary Orbs and Motions, and of the true and natural Equation of Time, and of other chief Uranometrical Matters, and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequent Unexactneſs and great Imperfection of Planetary Tables, both General and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>urnal, has greatly contributed to the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Imperfections of this Mantical part of the Science; which being wholly grounded up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the other, can, even with the greateſt Care and Judgment, be no further perfect than that is ſo. But we hope that as the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer daily draws nearer to Perfection, by the Sagacity and Induſtry of many eminent Skillſmen, ſo will the other alſo, whoſe hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto Defects are altogether as excuſable, though I cannot ſay that its Errours are ſo too.</p>
               <p n="10">10. Many falſe and ignorant Pretenders, through a groundleſs Conceit of themſelves, or a baſe Ambition to be thought what they are not, or a ſhirkiſh Endeavour to flatter ſome Patron or Favourite, do give us for certain Signs of great Vertue, Wit, Wiſdom and Happineſs, ſuch Poſitions and Configu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations as happen'd in their own, or their ſoothed Minion's Nativity, how diſſonant ſoever to both Art, Nature, Reaſon and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience. And therefore, <hi>Mercury</hi> in the Houſe
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:63400:25"/>of <hi>Saturn</hi> or <hi>Mars,</hi> or in Reception or good Ray with either, or in Airy Signs, or he ſtrong in his own Dignities, or the Aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant or its Lord in either of his Houſes, muſt give a great Wit, and a very ingenious and judicious Perſon; and a Thouſand more ſuch Trifleries, whoſe Untruth is obvious and notorious, as being frequently found to be utterly falſe, and ſerve only to puff up Fools, and incapable Blockheads, as the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives of ſuch Poſitions very often are, (eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially <hi>Mercury</hi> in the Houſes, or in Conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction with the Perſons of <hi>Saturn</hi> or <hi>Mars,</hi>) with vain and idle Conceits of their Accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhments; and afford them Colour for Jackanapiſh Brags and Pretences, when they find ſuch Fables deliver'd by Men of Name, and in large, well bound, and neatly gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh'd Volumes, which to many Capacities gives great Credit to the Matter.</p>
               <p n="11">11. Others, in Spight and Malice to ſome particular Perſon, and to render him hated or contemned, in revenge of ſome (perhaps deſerved) ill Turn, do canker dly propoſe, as ſure Signs of ſome great Vice, Defect, or future Calamity, ſuch Poſitions, Radiations, and Directions as happen at the Birth, or in the Geniture of the ſaid maligned Party. Thus an Infortune in ill Aſpect to the Aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant, its Lord, the <hi>Sun,</hi> or <hi>Moon,</hi> muſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibly betoken a Villain, or wicked Perſon.
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:63400:26"/>
                  <hi>Mercury</hi> cadent, weak, or afflicted; one void of Wit and Judgment: And Millions more of ſuch forged Sotteries; which, when attended with the aforeſaid Circumſtances, do glibly go down with many for real Truths, to the Abaſhment of many honeſt and ingenious Perſons, in whoſe Nativities they are often to be met with.</p>
               <p n="12">12. Such as ſtudy this Science, do almoſt wholly and generally confine their Endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to only ſome one part of it; which is a grand Reaſon of their making ſo ſlow Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances therein, and being all their Lives ſo far ſhort of any competent Perfection: There being many things diſcoverable in each Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Branch thereof, that may be very helpful to a right Underſtanding of every of the other Branches; and will not ſo rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily be found, nor fit Opportunities of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covering them be ſo frequently met with by ſuch as apply themſelves to one part alone. And the Part or Branch thus chiefly purſued, is that of Nativities; which, as things com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly happen, is of all others the unfitteſt, in regard that not only the true Moment is uſually much miſ-given, but oftentimes the Day, and ſometimes the Year alſo: And even when the true Day and Hour of Birth are given, yet by the Over-ſight of the Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culator or Publiſher, the Places of all or ſome of the Planets are amiſs, by Errour in
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:63400:26"/>Computation, or Miſtake of the Day in their <hi>Ephemeris.</hi> Of all which kinds of Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour I could give full Proof in ſundry Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vities now publick, and which paſs current for true ones: Whereby Learners and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perimentators are often greatly puzzl'd and diſtracted, as finding no Harmony in the ſeveral Genitures examin'd about any one Accident or Circumſtance, for the finding and framing a Rule concerning it. So that Beginners have need to try a Nativity throughly in all thoſe Reſpects, before they receive it as a Foundation of Knowledge or Practice.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="hymn">
            <pb n="50" facs="tcp:63400:27"/>
            <head>DAVID'S Aſtrological Hymn.</head>
            <div type="Psalm">
               <head>Pſalm viij. 1.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>GReat Sov'reign Lord of all created Things,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe is the Breath and Life of ev'ry Creature:</l>
                  <l>How moſt illuſtrious, O thou King of Kings,</l>
                  <l>Is thy great Name through all the Frame of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture!</l>
                  <l>Who haſt for ever firmly fix'd on high</l>
                  <l>The Boundleſs Glory of thy Majeſty.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>When with attentive Thoughts, and ſtedfaſt Eyes,</l>
                  <l>The Heav'ns, thy Works, I ponder and behold,</l>
                  <l>The Moon and Stars, and all that in the Skies</l>
                  <l>Thou didst create, and hourly dost uphold;</l>
                  <l>Oh, What is Man, I wondring cry! that he,</l>
                  <l>So frail! ſo vile! regarded is by thee.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="Psalm">
               <head>Pſalm xix. 1.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>THE ſpangled Heav'ns admired Face and Frame</l>
                  <l>Do thy Almighty Power and Praiſe declare:</l>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:63400:27"/>
                  <l>So doth the ſpreading Firmament proclaim</l>
                  <l>Thy Handy-work, thy Wiſdom, and thy Care</l>
                  <l>Each ſeveral Day doth plainly Speech expreſs:</l>
                  <l>And every Night doth Man with Knowledge bleſs.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>There is no Speech that enters Humane Ear,</l>
                  <l>Nor Language ſpoke within the World's wide Coaſt,</l>
                  <l>But where they do the Voice diſtinctly hear</l>
                  <l>Of Heav'n's reſplendent All-ſurrounding Host;</l>
                  <l>Whoſe guiding Line doth to all Nations reach:</l>
                  <l>Their Words all Corners of the World do teach.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
